Have you ever noticed how that little ING
ending in English seems to be, well,
everywhere?
It shows up on verbs, it acts like a noun,
it describes things, I mean, it's a real
workhorse of the language.
But let's be honest, it can also be a
little bit of a puzzle.
So today we are going to crack the code on
one of its most important and maybe most
confusing jobs. Okay, let's just dive
right in.
We're going to start by looking at a super
common point of confusion, a place where
this simple three-letter ending creates a
real head scratcher.
So here's the mystery we're gonna solve
today.
On the surface, the two sentences you're
about to see
look almost the same, but that one word
listening
is pulling off a pretty clever trick.
The question is, what exactly is it doing?
Okay, here we go.
In that first sentence, her hobby is
listening to the radio.
The word listening is basically the name
of an activity.
It's a thing, right? It's her hobby.
But in the second one, she is listening to
the radio.
It's all about action. It's what she's
doing right this very second.
So same word, totally different jobs. How
is that possible?
What is going on here? Well, it's time to
pull back the curtain
and solve this mystery by introducing the
hero of our story today.
It's a special kind of word that
absolutely loves to go undercover.
It's called a gerund. And you know, the
absolute best way to think
about a gerund is that it's a verb, an
action word,
that puts on an in costume so it can sneak
around
and do the job of a noun. It's a master of
disguise,
turning an action into a thing you can
talk about.
And really, it all boils down to this
simple formula.
You take a verb, any verb, like read or
swim,
you slap ing on the end and boom,
it's not just an action anymore, it's a
noun.
It's the activity of reading or the
concept of swimming.
It's no longer just something you do, it's
the idea of doing it.
So now that we know its secret identity,
Let's go on a little safari and see where
the shape-shifting word likes to show up.
It has a few favorite hangouts in a
sentence.
Turns out you can usually find gerunds in
one of three main spots.
They can be the subject, you know, the
main character of the whole sentence.
They pop up after b-verbs, like is, am, or
are, and they can be the object, the thing
getting the action from another verb.
Let's take a look at each one.
So in this sentence, what's actually good
for your health?
It's not just the vegetables, right? It's
the activity of eating them.
That gerund eating is the subject of the
entire sentence.
It's the thing this whole sentence is
about.
Now check out the structure here.
It's basically a perfect little equation.
His job equals helping students. See that?
The gerund helping comes right after the
verb IS and it renames or defines what the
job
IS. His job IS that activity. And here we
have our third spot.
What did he start? He started laughing.
The gerund laughing is the direct object
of the verb started.
It's the thing that received the action.
Simple as that.
Okay, seems pretty straightforward, right?
Verb plus ing equals a noun. Got it.
But you know, just when you think you've
got English figured out, it loves to throw
a curveball.
It turns out the gerund has a rival,
something that often tries to do the exact
same job.
And here it is, the rival we were talking
about, the two infinitive.
Just look at these two sentences. One uses
the gerund, speaking.
The other uses the infinitive, to speak.
But here's the wild part, they mean the
exact same thing.
In a lot of cases, they are totally
interchangeable.
And that of course leads us to the million
dollar question.
If they can often do the same job, can we
just swap them out whenever we feel like
it?
And the answer, maybe not so surprisingly
for English, is a big fat no.
You see, some verbs are just picky. They
have their preferences.
Verbs like enjoy and finish, for instance.
They only want to work with a gerund.
You can say, I enjoy playing golf, but I
enjoy to play golf.
It just sounds wrong to a native speaker,
doesn't it?
These verbs demand a gerund as their
partner.
All right, let's bring it all home.
Now that we know what a gerund is and what
it isn't, we have all the tools we need
to finally solve that mystery from the
very beginning.
So let's go back to the scene of the
crime.
What is really the difference here?
One sentence is talking about the hobby of
listening, which is a noun, a concept.
And the other is talking about the action
of listening, which is a verb, something
happening
right now. How can we tell them apart for
good? Here it is.
This is the definitive test.
In that first sentence, her hobby is
collecting stamps.
The ing word is a gerant. Why? Because you
can use an equal sign.
Her hobby equals the activity of
collecting.
They are the same concept.
a noun. But in the second one, she IS
collecting stamps, that ING word is just
doing its normal
verb job. Its fancy name is a present
participle, and it's just showing an
ongoing action.
The equals test totally fails here. She
does not equal collecting. She is a
person, collecting
is the action she is doing. That's the key
difference.
So there you have it. You know the secret.
You cannot tell the difference between a
verb wearing a noun costume and a verb
that's just, you know, being a verb. Let's
Let's wrap this up into your new grammar
superpower.
Think of this as your personal three-step
Jaren spotting guide.
Step one, find the word ending in ING.
Easy enough.
Step two, ask yourself, is this thing
acting like a noun?
Is it naming an activity or an idea?
And finally, step three, check its job. Is
it the subject?
Is it the object?
Or, and this is the big one, does it pass
that equals test after the verb is?
If the answer is yes, congratulations,
you've spotted a Jaren in the wild.
The gerund is just this brilliant little
piece of English grammar that lets us talk
about
actions as if they were actual things.
It's what lets us say running is my
favorite exercise, or I really hate
cleaning.
So now that you know it's secret identity,
the only question left is where are you
going
to spot this amazing verb in disguise
next?