Hey everyone, and welcome.
In this explainer, we are going to unlock
a total English superpower.
How to talk about all the things you
didn't do. Ready?
Let's get into it.
Okay, let's start with a situation we've
all been in, right?
It's the end of the day, you're super
tired, and oops, you didn't do your
homework.
But how do you say that in English?
Yesterday, I homework not do?
Eh, that doesn't sound quite right, does
it?
Well, stick with me because by the end of
this, you'll know exactly how to say it.
And trust me, it's way easier than you
think.
Alright, let's start putting the pieces of
this puzzle together.
First up, we've got to figure out the
right way to say you didn't do something
in the
past.
Now to learn how to talk about the past,
we're actually going to start with
something
you probably already know really well, the
present tense.
Think of this as a quick warm-up before we
totally level up your English game.
So in the present tense, you've got to
remember two different words, right?
You use don't for I, you and they, but
then you have to switch over to doesn't
for he
and she. It can be kind of annoying to
keep track of both of them.
But what if I told you that talking about
the past is actually easier?
Yeah, for real.
Forget about juggling two words, I'm about
to hand you a magic key that unlocks
everything.
And that magic key is this one simple
word, didn't, boom, that's it.
This one little word is going to do all
the heavy lifting for us whenever we talk
about
something that happened in the past. And
here's why it's so awesome.
It doesn't matter who you're talking
about, I, you, he, she, they, it's always
didn't.
Just one word for everybody.
So much easier than don't and doesn't,
right?
Okay, now, like any powerful magic key,
there is one tiny secret role you have to
know to
use it correctly.
So listen up, because this next part is
super, super important.
So here's the secret.
When you use didn't, the verb that comes
after it gets to just relax and go back to
its
original simple form. And why is that?
Well, it's because didn't is like the
superhero here.
It's already doing all the work of showing
that we're talking about the past.
Let's see how it works.
You might say, I played tennis, and you've
got that ED on the end.
But once you bring in our magic word,
poof, I didn't play tennis.
See that? The ED just vanishes.
Played goes right back to its original
form, play.
And this works even for those super tricky
irregular verbs.
You know the ones.
So you could say he went to London, which
is a really popular city for Americans to
visit by the way.
But if his plans changed, you'd say he
didn't go to London.
Went just snaps right back to its original
form, go. Cool, huh?
Okay, everybody, listen up, because this
right here is the number one trap that
students fall into.
They'll say something like, he didn't
lived using both did and the ed ending.
But you are not going to make that
mistake, are you?
Nope, because now you know the secret
rule.
Didn't has all the power, so the verb
doesn't need to.
All right, you've got the magic word and
you know the secret rule.
Are you ready to take it for a spin?
Let's do a quick final check to make sure
you are a total didn't master.
Okay, challenge number one. The sentence
is, I studied math last night. Now pay
attention to
how study changed to studied. How would
you make this sentence negative? Think
about the rule.
And the answer is, I didn't study math
last night. Yes, you nailed it. You
remembered that
studied has to go all the way back to its
base form study. Fantastic job.
Next up, she walked to work. You know, if
she lives in a huge American city like New
New York, she probably didn't walk to
work.
Most people take the subway. So how would
you say it? You got it.
She didn't walk to work.
The magic word didn't pops in and that
little ED from walked just completely
disappears.
It's really as simple as that.
Alright it is time for the final boss
challenge.
This one has an irregular verb which makes
it a little bit tougher.
The sentence is, we saw a great movie.
So how do you make this one negative? And
there it is!
We didn't see a great movie!
Saw goes right back to its original form,
C. You did it!
You defeated the final boss!
You are officially a master of the past
tense negative.
So let's wrap this all up.
When it comes down to it, the key takeaway
is just this one simple magic formula.
To talk about what you didn't do in the
past, all you need is didn't plus the
original verb. That's it. That's the whole
secret.
And now, it's your turn to use your brand
new superpower. What's one thing you
didn't
do today? Maybe you didn't eat your
vegetables, or you didn't watch TV? Try
making a sentence
for yourself right now. Thanks so much for
hanging out with me, and I'll see you in
the next one.