Have you ever really stopped to think about how we say numbers in English?
I mean, it seems pretty simple on the surface, but there's actually a hidden code,
a secret logic, right under our noses.
So, today, we're gonna go on a little journey,
and using this language textbook as our guide, we're gonna crack it.
So, let's kick things off with a mystery you've probably heard your whole life, but never really questioned.
We say fourteen, sixteen, seventeen,
so why in the world don't we say one-teen?
Or two-teen?
It just sounds wrong, right?
Well, that little bit of weirdness, that's our first big clue that there's a system at play here.
You know, every good code has a key,
and for English numbers, the key is a bunch of words that don't seem to follow any pattern at all.
These are the odd ones out, the special cases.
We have to learn them first, because they are the absolute foundation for the entire system.
So, here they are.
Every single one of these, from zero all the way to twelve, is a totally unique word.
There's no system here, no secret to figure out, you just have to know them.
Think of these as our main characters, the core pieces we're gonna use to build everything else.
Okay, so once you've got those first thirteen numbers locked in, we can finally move past the chaos.
Because right after the number twelve, the code starts to reveal itself.
We're about to find our very first real pattern.
And here it is, the first piece of the puzzle, the suffix teen.
Now it's not just some random ending, it's actually an old word that literally means plus ten.
So every time you hear that teen sound, you're basically hearing a tiny little math equation hidden right inside the word itself.
Just look at this.
You take one of our original numbers, like four, you tack on the teen suffix, and boom, you get fourteen.
Four plus ten.
It's that simple, it's that predictable.
See, the code actually works.
Of course, you know, English just loves to have its little quirks.
The teen system is fantastic, but it's got a few little exceptions that kind of show the language's age.
It's not thirteen, it's thirteen, and it's not fifteen, it's fifteen.
And with eighteen, we just get rid of that extra T.
They're just small spelling changes, but the core logic, a number plus ten, that stays exactly the same.
So the teen suffix gets us all the way from thirteen to nineteen.
But what happens next?
Well, the next piece of the code is another suffix that sounds almost the same.
T-Y.
And this one little change unlocks pretty much everything else up to one hundred.
Okay, this is probably the most important part.
Thirteen is three plus ten.
But thirty, that's three times ten.
So one is for adding, the other is for multiplying.
That one tiny little sound shift is the absolute key to counting all the way up to ninety-nine.
And once you have these T words down, building any other number is just like stacking blocks.
You just grab your ten block, let's say twenty, and you snap one of our original numbers right onto the end.
So twenty plus one gives you twenty-one.
And it just keeps on working, over and over.
Twenty-two, thirty-five, sixty-seven, all the way up to ninety-nine.
It's the same simple repeatable pattern.
The system is actually really elegant when you think about it.
No more memorizing, now we're just building.
Okay, so we've mastered everything from one to ninety-nine.
But, how do we get to the really big numbers?
Well, it turns out you only need a few more special words.
And these words act like massive building blocks that let us scale this whole system way, way up.
The first major checkpoint after ninety-nine is, of course, one hundred.
This one word opens up the ability to build every number all the way to nine hundred ninety-nine.
After that, the next big jump is to one thousand.
And you see that comma there? That's not just for looks.
It's a visual clue telling you that you've just hit a brand new, much more powerful building block.
And from a thousand, we take this enormous leap all the way to one million.
And honestly, that's pretty much it.
With just these few new level markers, we can now build almost any number you can possibly imagine.
Okay, so we've gathered all the pieces of our code.
We have our irregulars, we've got our teen and our teen rules, and we have our big building blocks.
Now it is time for the payoff.
Let's put our new knowledge to the test on a really big, complicated number.
Alright, here's our final challenge, taken straight out of the textbook.
Twenty million, two hundred fifty thousand, seven hundred seventeen.
I mean, that looks like a monster, right?
But now that we know the code, we can break it down no problem.
The secret is to just ignore the whole thing at first and focus only on the commas.
They act like little walls, breaking the number into small, manageable chunks.
All we have to do is read the number inside each chunk, like twenty or two hundred fifty,
and then just say the name of that chunk's level, so million or thousand.
It's like reading three small numbers instead of one giant one.
And there you have it.
Twenty million, two hundred fifty thousand, seven hundred seventeen.
We did it.
We took this massive, intimidating number, and we broke it down with the simple, logical rules we uncovered.
The code works perfectly.
Alright, now for a fun little encore.
We've pretty much mastered whole numbers, but what about decimals?
And how can that lead us to a, uh, delicious mathematical pun?
Believe it or not, the rule for decimals might be the simplest one of all.
You just say the whole number, then you say the word point, and then you just read out each digit one by one.
So 3.14 is never 3.14.
It's always 3.14.
Easy, right?
And this brings us to this great little cultural tidbit from our source material.
So, the number pi starts with 3.14.
In the US, March 14th is written as 3-14.
So naturally, it became Pi Day.
And because pi sounds exactly like pie, it's become a fun tradition to celebrate this math holiday by eating, well, pie.
So, what started with a strange little question about one teen ended with us cracking an entire linguistic code.
It just goes to show you that language is full of these amazing hidden systems, if you just know how to look.
Which, of course, leads to one final thought.
We've just figured out the secret of English numbers,
so what incredible patterns are just waiting to be discovered in all the other languages of the world?
Thank you.