Hey what's up everyone and welcome. Are
you ready to crack one of the biggest,
most useful
secret codes in English? Yup, I'm talking
about numbers. You see them everywhere and
after this
you're gonna be able to say even the
craziest, biggest numbers without breaking
a sweat.
Trust me, it's gonna be fun. Okay, let's
dive in. Whoa, okay let's just jump right
in with a big one,
huh? Take a look at this number. If you're
thinking there is no way I can say that,
That's totally normal. But hey, here's a
little spoiler.
That number is 20,250,717.
And believe it or not, by the end of our
time together,
you'll know exactly how to say it too. You
will!
See, here's the thing.
English numbers aren't just a long, random
list of words
you have to memorize. Not at all. They're
a system, a pattern.
It's kind of like a secret code.
So our mission today, should you choose to
accept it,
is to crack that code together. piece by
piece. Ready? Let's do this.
First things first. Every single giant
number, even that crazy one we just saw,
is built from a few tiny, simple parts.
Think of them like Legos, our building
blocks.
Once you know these few little pieces, you
can build absolutely anything.
And here they are, our main characters.
These are the absolute basics.
Let's just say them slowly and clearly. I
want you to listen and maybe even say them
quietly
with me. Ready? Zero. One. Two. Three.
Four. Five. Six. Seven. Eight. Nine. Ten.
Awesome.
This is your foundation. Seriously. Nail
these and you've basically won half the
bow.
Now every secret code has a couple of
rebels, right? You know, characters that
don't really
play by the rules. Well, in English
numbers, meet our two special agents.
Eleven and twelve.
These two are totally unique, so you just
have to memorize them.
But the good news?
These are pretty much the last weird ones
for a bit.
So just lock them in your memory, 11 and
12.
Okay, so you've got the basic crew.
Are you ready for the first secret rule of
our code?
This is where the fun really starts,
because this one rule is going to unlock a
whole
group of numbers for you, just like that.
Let's check it out.
The first magic word is teen.
You just take a number you already know,
like 4, and you snap teen onto the end.
And boom, 14.
Now pay attention here, because there are
two little exceptions.
It's not 13, it's 13, and not 15, but 15.
A little weird, I know, but you can still
hear that pattern, right?
You got this. And here they are, your
whole teen toolkit.
Let's listen for that magic sound at the
end of each one.
15, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19.
Hear that? That strong sound at the end?
That's the secret.
Once you get that trick, you know all of
them. Great job!
All right, everybody, deep breath, this
next slide. This is a big one.
This is maybe the most important slide in
our whole mission.
This is the number one mistake people
make, but you, you are not going to make
it.
Not after this. This is the boss level.
Okay, look closely.
The difference between 13 and 30, or 14
and 40, is all about stress.
It's about where you put the energy, the
punch, in the word.
For the teens, the energy is at the end.
Listen close, 13.
Hear how my voice goes up at the end? Now
listen to this, 30.
The energy is right at the start. Let's
try another one, 14, 40.
You hear that difference? It's huge.
So what's the one thing to remember? It's
all about the stress.
Let's do one more together. Come on, try
it with me.
Even if you feel a little silly, it really
helps. Say it loud, 16.
Now say 60. Yes, that's it.
Practicing just like that is how you
master it for good.
You are doing so great. Yes, you did it.
You just totally beat the boss level of
English numbers.
I'm serious, that was the hardest part.
From here on out, we're just combining the
puzzle pieces
you already know how to use to build even
bigger and cooler numbers.
Okay, building numbers from 21 to 99 is
super easy.
It's like a simple two-step formula.
Step one, grab a T number, like 20.
Step two, add a single number from one to
nine, like three.
Stick them together and bam, 23.
It works every single time, 71, 55, 89.
See, you can do all of them now. All
right, you are crushing this.
So let's level up one more time. We've got
200 on the screen.
How do we say this one?
Well, this is where we hit another little
trap, a really common mistake, but one
you're about
to learn how to dodge like a pro.
Okay, so your brain probably wants to say
200s.
I mean, it makes perfect sense, right?
There are two of them.
But hold on. That's the trap.
It feels right, but it's actually
incorrect.
But don't you worry, the fix is super
easy.
And here's the super simple fix.
You just say the number, and then the word
hundred. That's it.
200, 800, 500.
The words hundred, thousand, and million
are kind of lazy.
They don't like to add an S on the end
when there's a specific number in front.
Just remembering that one tip will make
your English sound so much more natural.
And now, look at how we just start
stacking those Legos we learned about.
For 243, you just say the first part, 200,
and then you say the next part you
already know, 43. For a big one like 4567,
you just go piece by piece. 4567. Oh, and
by the way, you'll hear people say and in
there like 243. That's totally cool, too.
You can use it or not.
Okay, you have been working so hard, and
you've learned all the main rules of the
code. So
as a reward, I think you've earned a
little bonus level, a fun one, where
English gets
It's a little silly. You've definitely
seen this number in math class.
Good old pie. But what do we do with that
little dot in the middle?
How do we say numbers that have a decimal
point?
Okay, you're not gonna believe how easy
this is.
This might be the easiest rule of the
whole day.
For the dot, you just say the word point.
And then for the numbers that come after
it, you say them one by one.
So 3.14 becomes 3.14.
It's not 3.14, nope, just 3.14.
Super easy, right?
And here's where English gets a little
weird and fun.
The word for the number P-I, pi, sounds
exactly the same as the word
for a delicious dessert, P-I-E, pi.
And that is exactly why in America, March
14th, which we write as 314,
is called pi day and people celebrate by
eating pi. It's a silly joke,
but it's a great way to remember the
number. And that's it.
Just like that, you've done it.
You made it all the way through the code
book.
You learned the secret rules, you dodged
the tricky traps, all of it.
You now have the keys to say pretty much
any number you can think of in English.
So let's look at your final reward. So
think of this slide
as your official number master code book.
It's your quick cheat sheet
with all the key code words we learned
today. It's all right here.
From the basics to our special agents 11
and 12,
to those tricky teens and teens all the
way up to a million.
You know how all these parts work together
now? You totally earn this.
So now I've got a final challenge for you.
You have the code, you know the secrets,
you have the confidence.
So what's the biggest, wildest, most
amazing number you can think of?
Go find one today and say it out loud in
English. You can do it.
Awesome work today. And thanks so much for
cracking the code with me.